<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-psarkar-idr-bgp-ls-node-admin-tag-extension-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
     <title>Advertising Per-node Admin Tags in BGP Link-State Advertisements</title>


    <author initials="P." surname="Sarkar" fullname="Pushpasis Sarkar" role="editor">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>Electra, Exora Business Park</street>
      <city>Bangalore</city>
      <region>KA</region>
      <code>560103</code>
      <country>India</country>
      </postal>
      <email>psarkar@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Gredler" initials="H." surname="Gredler">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
      <city>Sunnyvale</city>
      <region>CA</region>
      <code>94089</code>
      <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <email>hannes@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S" surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->
        <!-- <phone/> -->
        <!-- <facsimile/> -->
        <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>
        <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="16" month="February" year="2015" />

    <workgroup>Inter-Domain Routing</workgroup>

    <keyword>BGP-LS</keyword>
    <keyword>Admin-Tag</keyword>
    <keyword>Traffic Engineering</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the protocol extensions to collect per-node 
      administrative tags adevertised in IGP Link State advertisements and  
      disseminate the same in BGP Link-State advertisement protocol, to facilitate 
      inter-AS TE applications that may need the same per-node administrative tags  
      to associate a subset of network devices spanning across more than one AS 
      with a specific functionality.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
</front>

<middle>

  <section title="Introduction" anchor='intro'>
    <t> Advertising Per-node Administrative Tags in Link State protocols like 
    IS-IS <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/> and OSPF 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-ospf-node-admin-tag"/> allows adding an optional  
    operational capability, that allows tagging and grouping of the nodes in  
    a IGP domain. This, among other applications, allows simple management and 
    easy control over route and path selection, based on local configured 
    policies. However per-node administrative tags advertised in IGP 
    advertisements let network operators associate nodes within a single AS 
    (if not a single area). This limits the use of such per-node administrative 
    tags and applications that need to associate a subset of network devices
    spanning across multiple AS with a specific functionality cannot use them.</t>

    <t>To address the need for applications that require visibility
    into LSDB across IGP areas, or even across ASes, the BGP-LS
    address-family/sub-address-family have been defined that allows
    BGP to carry LSDB information. The BGP Network Layer
    Reachability Information (NLRI) encoding format for BGP-LS and a
    new BGP Path Attribute called BGP-LS attribute are defined in
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-ls-distribution"></xref>. The
    identifying key of each LSDB object, namely a node, a link or a
    prefix, is encoded in the NLRI and the properties of the object
    are encoded in the BGP-LS attribute. <xref
    target="MECHANISM-CONSUMER-PRODUCER"/> describes a typical
    deployment scenario. In each IGP area, one or more nodes are
    configured with BGP-LS. These BGP speakers form an IBGP mesh by
    connecting to one or more route-reflectors. This way, all BGP
    speakers - specifically the route-reflectors - obtain LSDB
    information from all IGP areas (and from other ASes from EBGP
    peers). An external component connects to the route-reflector to
    obtain this information (perhaps moderated by a policy regarding
    what information is sent to the external component, and what
    information isn't).</t>

    <figure anchor="MECHANISM-CONSUMER-PRODUCER"
            title="Link State info collection">
      <artwork>
                        +------------+
                        |  Consumer  |
                        +------------+
                              ^
                              |
                              v
                    +-------------------+
                    |    BGP Speaker    |         +-----------+
                    | (Route-Reflector) |         | Consumer  |
                    +-------------------+         +-----------+
                          ^   ^   ^                       ^
                          |   |   |                       |
          +---------------+   |   +-------------------+   |
          |                   |                       |   |
          v                   v                       v   v
    +-----------+       +-----------+             +-----------+
    |    BGP    |       |    BGP    |             |    BGP    |
    |  Speaker  |       |  Speaker  |    . . .    |  Speaker  |
    +-----------+       +-----------+             +-----------+
          ^                   ^                         ^
          |                   |                         |
         IGP                 IGP                       IGP
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <t> For the purpose of advertising per-node administrative tags within BGP 
    Link-State advertisements, a new Node Attribute TLV to be carried in the 
    corresponding BGP-LS Node NLRI is proposed. For more details on the Node 
    Attribute TLVs please refer to section 3.3.1 in 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-ls-distribution"/></t>

  </section>

  <section title='Per-Node Administrative Tag'>
    <t> An administrative Tag is a 32-bit integer value that can be used to identify 
    a group of nodes in the entire routing domain. The new sub-TLV specifies one or 
    more administrative tag values. A BGP Link-State speaker that also participates 
    in the IGP link state advertisements exchange may learn one or more per-node 
    administrative tags advertised by another router in the same IGP domain. Such 
    BGP-LS speaker shall encode the same set of per-node administrative tags in the 
    corresponding Node Attribute TLV representing the network device that originated 
    the per-node administrative tags.</t>

    <t> The per-node administrative tags advertised in IGP link state advertisements 
    will have either per-area(or levels in IS-IS)scope or 'global' scope. Operator 
    may choose to a set of per-node administrative tags across areas (or levels in 
    IS-IS) and another advertise set of per-node  administrative tags within the 
    specific area (or level). But evidently two areas within the same AS or two 
    different may use the same per-node administrative tag for different purposes. 
    In such case applications will need to distinguish between the per-area(or level) 
    scoped administrative tags originated from a specific node against those originated 
    from the same node with 'global' scope.</t>

    <t>A BGP-LS router in a given AS while copying the per-node administrative tags 
    learnt from IGP link-state advertisements, MUST also copy the scope associated 
    with the per-node administrative tags. Refer to <xref target="node-admin-tag-tlv"/> 
    for how to encode the associated scope of a per-node administrative tags as well.</t>

    <t>To be able to distinguish between the significance of a per-area(or level) 
    administrative tag learnt in one area, from that advertised in another area, 
    or another AS, any applications receiving such a BGP-LS advertisements MUST 
    consider the scope associated with each per-node administrative tag with 'per-area
    (or per-level) along with the area(or level in IS-IS) associated with corresponding 
    IGP link state advertisement and the AS number associated with the originating node.
    The area(or level) associated with corresponding IGP link state advertisement 
    and the AS number associated with the originating node can be derived from  
    appropriate node attributes (already defined in 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-ls-distribution">BGP-LS</xref>) attached with the 
    corresponding Node NLRI.</t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="bgp-ls-extension"
           title="BGP-LS Extensions for Per-Node Administrative Tags">
    <t>The BGP-LS NLRI can be a node NLRI, a link NLRI or a prefix NLRI. The  
    corresponding BGP-LS attribute is a node attribute, a link attribute or 
    a prefix attribute. <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-ls-distribution">BGP-LS</xref> 
    defines the TLVs that map link-state information to BGP-LS NLRI and BGP-LS
    attribute. This document adds an new Node Attribute TLV called 'Node Admin 
    Tag TLV' to encode per-node administrative tags information.</t>

    <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/> defines the 'Per-node 
    Admin Tag' sub-TLV in the Router Capability TLV (type 242) in IS-IS 
    Link State PDUs to encode per-node administrative tags. Similarly 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/> defines the 'Per-node 
    Administrative Tag' TLV in OSPF Router Information LSAs to encode per-node 
    administrative tags in OSPF Link State update packets. The per-node 
    administrative tags TLVs learnt from the IGP link state advertisements 
    of a specific node will all be inserted in a new Node Admin Tag TLV 
    and added to the corresponding Node are mapped to the corresponding 
    BGP-LS Node NLRI. Per-node administrative tags from IGP advertisements are 
    mapped to the corresponding Node Admin Tag TLV in the following way.</t>

    <texttable anchor="node-attribute_tlv"
               title="Node Admin Tag TLV Mapping from IGP">
      <ttcol align="center">TLV Code Point</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Length</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="right">IS-IS TLV/sub-TLV</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="right">OSPF LSA/TLV</ttcol>

      <c>TBD</c>
      <c>Node Admin Tag TLV</c>
      <c>Variable</c>
      <c><eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-isis-node-admin-tag-00#section-3.1">242/TBD</eref></c>
      <c><eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-ospf-node-admin-tag-00#section-4.1">RI-LSA/TBD</eref></c>
    </texttable>

    <section anchor="node-admin-tag-tlv" 
             title='Node Admin Tag TLV'>
      <t>The new Node Administrative Tag TLV, like other BGP-LS Node Attribute TLVs, is formatted 
      as Type/Length/Value (TLV)triplets. <xref target="nodeadmintagtlv"/> below shows the 
      format of the new TLV.</t>

      <figure anchor="nodeadmintagtlv" title="BGP Link-State Node Administrative Tag TLV">
        <artwork>
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |              Type             |             Length            | 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |            Flags              |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                   Administrative Tag #1                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                   Administrative Tag #2                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  //                                                             //
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                   Administrative Tag #N                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

   Type :  A 2-octet field specifiying code-point of the new 
           sub-TLV type. Code-point: TBA (suggested 1040)

   Length: A 2-octet field that indicates the length of the value
           portion in octets and will be a multiple of 4 octets
           dependent on the number of tags advertised.

   Value:  A 2-octet 'Flags' field, followed by a sequence of multiple 
           4 octets defining the administrative tags.

     Flags: A 2-octet field that carries flags associated with 
            all the administrative flags encoded in this TLV. 
            Following is the format of this field.

             0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
            +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            |L|            Reserved         | 
            +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

            The following bit flags are defined:

            L bit : If the L bit is set (1), it signifies that 
                    all administrative flags encoded in this 
                    TLV has per-area(or level in IS-IS) scope,
                    and should not be mixed with ones with same
                    value but with 'global' scope (L bit reset
                    to 0).

        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This new type of 'Node Admin Tag' TLVs can ONLY be added to the Node 
      Attribute associated with the Node NLRI that originates the corresponding 
      per-node administrative tags in IGP domain.</t>

      <t>All the per-node administrative tags with 'per-area' (or per-level) scope, 
      originated by a single node in IGP domain SHALL be re-originated in a single 
      'Node Admin Tag' TLV and inserted in the Node NLRI generated for the same node. 
      Similarly, all the per-node administrative tags with 'global' scope originated 
      by the same node in IGP domain SHALL be re-originated in another 'Node Admin Tag' 
      TLV and inserted in the same Node NLRI generated for the originating node. Multiple 
      instances of a TLV may be generated by the BGP-lS router for a given node in the 
      IGP domain. This MAY happen if the original node's link state advertisement carries 
      more than 16383 per-node administrative groups and a single TLV does not 
      provide sufficient space. As such multiple occurence of the 'Node Admin Tag' 
      TLVs under a single BGP LS NLRI is cumulative.</t>

     <t>While copying per-node administrative tags from IGP link-state advertisements 
     to corresponding BGP-LS advertisements, the said BGP-LS speaker MAY run all the 
     per-node administrative flags through a locally configured policy that selects which 
     ones should be exported and which ones not. And then the per-node administrative 
     tag is copied to the BGP-LS advertisement if it is permitted to do so by the said
     policy.</t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title='Elements of Procedure'>
    <t> Meaning of the Per-node administrative tags is generally opaque to 
    BGP Link-State protocol. Router advertising the per-node administrative 
    tag (or tags) may be configured to do so without knowing (or even explicitly 
    supporting) functionality implied by the tag.</t>

    <t> Interpretation of tag values is specific to the administrative domain
    of a particular network operator. The meaning of a per-node administrative 
    tag is defined by the network local policy and is controlled via the 
    configuration. However multiple administrative domain owners may agree on 
    a common meaning implied by a administrative tag for mutual benefit.</t>

    <t> The semantics of the tag order has no meaning. There is no implied 
    meaning to the ordering of the tags that indicates a certain operation 
    or set of operations that need to be performed based on the ordering.</t>

    <t> Each tag SHOULD be treated as an independent identifier that MAY be 
    used in policy to perform a policy action. Per-node administrative tags 
    carried by the Node Admin Tag TLV SHOULD be used to indicate a independent 
    characteristics of the node in IGP domain that originated it. The TLV 
    SHOULD be considered as an unordered list. Whilst policies may be implemented 
    based on the presence of multiple tags (e.g., if tag A AND tag B are present), 
    they MUST NOT be reliant upon the order of the tags (i.e., all policies 
    should be considered commutative operations, such that tag A preceding 
    or following tag B does not change their outcome).</t>

    <t> For more details on guidance on usage of per-node administrative 
    tags please refer to 
    <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-isis-node-admin-tag-00#section-4">section 4</eref> 
    in <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/>. </t>
  </section>

  <section title='Applications'>
    <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/> and 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-ospf-node-admin-tag"/> present some applications of node 
    administrative tags.</t>

    <t>The policy-based Explicit routing use case can be extended to inter-area or 
    inter-AS scenarios where an end to end path needs to avoid or include nodes that 
    have particular properties. Following are some examples.

    <list style="numbers">
      <t>Geopolitical routing : preventing traffic from country A to country B 
      to cross country C. In this case, we may use node administrative tags to 
      encode geographical information (country). Path computation will be required 
      to take into account node administrative tag to permit avoidance of nodes 
      belonging to country C.</t>

      <t>Legacy node avoidance : in some specific cases, it is interesting for 
      service-provider to force some traffic to avoid legacy nodes in the network.
      For example, legacy nodes may not be carrier class (no high availability), 
      and service provider wants to ensure that critical traffic only uses nodes
      that are providing high availability.</t>
    </list>
    </t>

    <t>In case of inter-AS Traffic-Engineering applications, different ASes SHOULD 
    share their admin tag policies. They MAY also need to agree upon some common 
    tagging policy for specific applications.</t> 

    <t> For more details on some possible applications with per-node 
    administrative tags please refer to 
    <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-isis-node-admin-tag-00#section-5">section 5</eref> 
    in <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-node-admin-tag"/>. </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document requests assigning code-points from the registry 
    for BGP-LS attribute TLVs based on table <xref
    target="BGPLSCODEPOINTS"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Manageability" title="Manageability Considerations">
    <t>This section is structured as recommended in <xref
    target="RFC5706"></xref>.</t>

    <section anchor="Operational-Considerations"
             title="Operational Considerations">

      <section anchor="Operations" title="Operations">

        <t>Existing BGP and BGP-LS operational procedures apply.
        No new operation procedures are defined in this document.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section anchor="TLVSUMMARY" title="TLV/Sub-TLV Code Points Summary">
    <t>This section contains the global table of all TLVs/Sub-TLVs defined in
    this document.</t>
    
    <texttable anchor="BGPLSCODEPOINTS"
               title="Summary Table of TLV/Sub-TLV Codepoints">
      <ttcol align="center">TLV Code Point</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="center">Length</ttcol>

      <!-- BGP-LS Attribute TLVs -->

      <!-- Node Attributes TLVs -->

      <c>1040</c>
      <c>Node Admin Tag</c>
      <c>variable</c>
    </texttable>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>Procedures and protocol extensions defined in this document do not
    affect the BGP security model. See the 'Security Considerations' section
    of <xref target="RFC4271"/> for a discussion of BGP security.  Also refer
    to <xref target="RFC4272"/> and <xref target="RFC6952"/>
    for analysis of security issues for BGP.</t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>TBD.</t>
  </section>
</middle>

<back>
  <references title='Normative References'>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>
  </references>

  <references title='Informative References'>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4272.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5706.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6952.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-isis-node-admin-tag-00.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-ospf-node-admin-tag-00.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-ls-distribution-07.xml"?>
  </references>
</back>
</rfc>

